My journey to coming here today
رحلتي للمجئ إلى هنا اليوم
started in 1974.
بدأت عام 1974.
That's me with the funny gloves.
تلك أنا أرتدى القفازات المضحكة
I was 17 and going on a peace walk.
كنت في السابعة عشر من عمري أشارك في مسيرة سلمية
What I didn't know though, was most of those people, standing there
ما لم أكن أعرفه حينها، أن معظم هؤلاء الناس، الواقفين هناك
with me, were Moonies.
معي، كانوا من المونيس (أعضاء كنيسة التوحيد).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And within a week
وخلال أسبوع
I had come to believe
توصلت الى الاعتقاد
that the second coming of Christ had occurred,
بأن البعث الثاني المسيح قد حدث،
that it was Sun Myung Moon,
وكان ذلك سون ميونغ مون،
and that I had been specially chosen and prepared by God
وأنه قد تم إختياري خصوصاً وقد أعدني الله
to be his disciple.
لأكون تلميذته.
Now as cool as that sounds,
الآن كما يبدو هذا لطيفاً،
my family was not that thrilled with this.
لم تكن عائلتي سعيدة بهذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And they tried everything they could to get me out of there.
وقد حاولوا كل شئ بإمكانهم لإخراجي من هناك.
There was an underground railroad of sorts
كانت هناك انواع من أنفاق سكك الحديد تحت الارض
that was going on during those years. Maybe some of you remember it.
التي كانت تحدث خلال تلك السنوات. ربما يتذكرها بعضكم.
They were called deprogrammers.
كان يُطلق عليهم معيدي البرمجة.
And after about five long years
وبعد حوالي خمسة سنوات
my family had me deprogrammed.
أستطاعت أسرتي إعادة برمجتي.
And I then became a deprogrammer.
وبعد ذلك أصبحت معيدة برمجة.
I started going out on cases.
وبدأت في علاج الحالات.
And after about five years of doing this,
وبعد حوالي خمسة سنوات من العمل (إعادة البرمجة)
I was arrested for kidnapping.
تم اعتقالي بتهمة الاختطاف.
Most of the cases I went out on
معظم الحالات التي راعيتها
were called involuntary.
سُميّت بغير التطوعية.
What happened was that the family
ما حدث هو أن تلك الأسرة
had to get their loved ones some safe place somehow.
توجب عليها أخذ أبنائها لمكان ما آمن.
And so they took them to some safe place.
ولذا فقد أخذوهم لبعض الأماكن الآمنة.
And we would come in and talk to them, usually for about a week.
وكنا نأتي للحديث معهم، عادة لمدة أسبوع.
And so after this happened,
وبعد أن حدث الإعتقال
I decided it was a good time to turn my back on this work.
قررت أنه الوقت المناسب لأن أترك هذا العمل.
And about 20 years went by.
ومضت حوالي 20 سنة.
There was a burning question though that would not leave me.
كان هناك ذلك السؤال الملتهب اللذي لا يفارقني..
And that was, "How did this happen to me?"
والسؤال هو، " كيف حدث لي هذا؟"
And in fact, what did happen to my brain?
وفي الحقيقة، ماذا حدث لعقلي؟
Because something did.
لأن شئ ما حدث
And so I decided to write a book, a memoir,
ولذا قررت أن أكتب كتاباً، ومذكرات،
about this decade of my life.
حول ذلك العقد من حياتي..
And toward the end of writing that book
وقرب الانتهاء من ذلك الكتاب
there was a documentary that came out.
ظهر فيلم وثائقي
It was on Jonestown.
وكان في منطقة جونزتاون
And it had a chilling effect on me.
وكان له تأثير كبير علي.
These are the dead in Jonestown.
هؤلاء موتى في منطقة جونزتاون.
About 900 people died that day,
حوالي 900 شخص ماتوا في ذلك اليوم.
most of them taking their own lives.
انتحر معظمهم
Women gave poison to their babies,
أعطت الأمهات السُم لأطفالهن،
and watched foam come from their mouths as they died.
وشاهدن الزبد يأتي من أفواههم أثناء موتهم
The top picture is a group of Moonies
الصورة في الأعلى لمجموعة من المونيس
that have been blessed by their messiah.
الذين تمت مباركتهم بواسطة "رسولهم"
Their mates were chosen for them.
تم إختيار شركاء حياتهم
The bottom picture is Hitler youth.
الصورة في الأسفل لشباب هتلر
This is the leg of a suicide bomber.
هذه قدم مفجّر انتحاري
The thing I had to admit to myself,
الشئ الذي يجب أن أعترف به لنفسي،
with great repulsion,
مع اشمئزاز شديد
was that I get it.
أنني أصبت به.
I understand how this could happen.
أفهم كيف يمكن أن يحدث هذا.
I understand how someone's brain,
أفهم كيف يتحور دماغ شخص ما،
how someone's mind can come to the place
كيف يصل عقل ما
where it makes sense --
إلى حيث يصبح ذلك معقولاً،
in fact it would be wrong, when your brain is working like that --
في الحقيقة سيكون هذا خطأ، عندما يعمل عقلك مثل ذلك،
not to try to save the world through genocide.
لا تحاول إنقاذ العالم عبر الإبادة الجماعية.
And so what is this? How does this work?
إذاً ما هذا؟ كيف يحدث ذلك؟
And how I've come to view what happened to me
وكيف توصلت لمعرفة أن ما حدث لي
is a viral, memetic infection.
هو عدوى متنقلة
For those of you who aren't familiar with memetics,
لأؤلئك الذين لا يعرفون العدوى الفكرية
a meme has been defined as
تم تعريف العدوى الفكرية
an idea that replicates in the human brain
كفكرة تنسخ نفسها في عقل الإنسان
and moves from brain to brain like a virus,
وتتنقل من عقل الى عقل مثل الفيروس،
much like a virus. The way a virus works is --
أشبه ما تكون بالفيروس. بنفس طريقة عمل الفيروس--
it can infect and do the most damage to someone
يمكن أن تصيب وتلحق أكبر الضرر بشخص ما
who has a compromised immune system.
لديه نظام مناعة مخترق.
In 1974, I was young, I was naive,
عام 1974، كنت يافعة، كنت ساذجة،
and I was pretty lost in my world.
وكنت ضائعة في عالمي
I was really idealistic.
كنت حقاً مثالية.
These easy ideas to complex questions are very appealing
كانت هذه الأفكار السهلة لأسئلة معقدة مغرية
when you are emotionally vulnerable.
خاصة إذا ما كنت غير مستقر عاطفيا
What happens is that
ما حدث هو
circular logic takes over.
أن المنطق الدائري كان المسيطر
"Moon is one with God.
" مون مُتحد مع الإله.
God is going to fix all the problems in the world.
سيقوم الإله بحل كل المشاكل في هذا العالم.
All I have to do is humbly follow.
كل ما يجب علي القيام به هو الإتبّاع
Because God is going to stop war and hunger --
لأن الإله سيقوم بإيقاف الحرب والجوع--
all these things I wanted to do --
وهذه الأشياء أردت أن أفعلها.
all I have to do is humbly follow.
كل ما يتوجب علي هو الطاعة العمياء.
Because after all, God is [working through] the messiah. He's going to fix all this."
لأن بعد كل شئ، الإله يعمل عبر "المسيح". سيقوم بإصلاح كل هذا."
It becomes impenetrable.
وتصبح تلك الأفكار قابلة لللإختراق.
And the most dangerous part of this
والجزء الأخطر في كل هذا
is that is creates "us" and "them,"
أن هذا ينشئ "نحن" و "هم،"
"right" and "wrong,"
"صواب" و "خطأ,"
"good" and "evil."
"خير" و "شر."
And it makes anything possible,
ويصبح كل شيء ممكن
makes anything rationalizable.
ومنطقي
And the thing is, though,
والفكرة هي، رغماً عن ذلك،
if you looked at my brain
اذا نظرت في عقلي
during those years in the Moonies --
خلال تلك السنوات مع المونيس--
neuroscience is expanding exponentially,
توسع علم الأعصاب بشكل ملحوظ،
as Ray Kurzweil said yesterday. Science is expanding.
كما قال راي كورزويل بالأمس. العلوم تتوسع.
We're beginning to look inside the brain.
بدأنا نبحث في داخل الدماغ.
And so if you looked at my brain, or any brain that's infected with
اذا نظرت داخل دماغي، أو أي عقل مُصاب
a viral memetic infection like this,
بعدوى فكرية مشابهة
and compared it to anyone in this room,
وقارنتموها مع أي شخص في هذه القاعة،
or anyone who uses critical thinking on a regular basis,
أو أي شخص يستخدم التفكير الناقد على أساس منتظم ،
I am convinced it would look very, very different.
أنا مقتنعة بأنه سيبدو مختلف جداً، جداً.
And that, strange as it may sound,
وذلك، كما يبدو غريباً،
gives me hope.
يعطيني الأمل.
And the reason that gives me hope
والسبب الذي يعطيني الأمل
is that the first thing is to admit
هو أن أول شيء هو الاعتراف
that we have a problem.
بأن لدينا مشكلة.
But it's a human problem. It's a scientific problem, if you will.
لكنها مشكلة إنسانية. ربما مشكلة علمية، اذا شئتم.
It happens in the human brain. There is no evil force out there to get us.
تحدث لعقل الإنسان. ليس هناك قوى شريرة تقودنا اليها.
And so this is something that, through research and education,
ولذا فإنه من خلال البحث والتعليم
I believe that we can solve.
أؤمن أننا سنقوم بحلها
And so the first step is to realize
ولذا فإن أول خطوة هي إدراك
that we can do this together,
أننا يمكن أن نفعل ذلك سوياً،
and that there is no "us" and "them."
وأنه لا يوجد "نحن" و "هم."
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً لكم. (تصفيق)